In ancient times,
thousands of lions roamed freely across Africa.
And prides living side by side.
There is still a place like this,
where the raw forces of nature are in control.
This is a kingdom where lions rule.
A special breed,
hunters of giants.
All mysteriously connected.
Luaha,
the story of ancient Africa.
The time of plenty is upon the land.
It slows the heartbeat of
Africa and brings rain to Ruaha.
This season has the power to transform.
To dilute,
to disarm.
This season has the power to restore.
But none of the water that fills the rivers can
wash away what happened here.
It
began in the dry season.
In a bend in the Mwagusi River,
even during the hottest,
driest summer,
there is always water here.
In a place called the Glade,
it is a sanctuary.
It is a haven,
the essence of life for all the animals of Ruaha.
But nothing is quite as it seems.
Strange things happen here.
Strange alliances.
In the natural world,
lions hunt baboons.
In the glade,
however,
generations of lion and baboon
families have coexisted.
A small pride of lions currently lives here.
Two wise old lionesses and their cubs.
Life is charmed.
Oh.
The Glade Pride follows the rules
set down by their forebears.
Never touch the baboons.
There's a reason for this.
There's nothing more dangerous than
a hungry lion.
Kudu,
drawn to the glade to drink.
Scatter in a heartbeat if they hear the alarm.
Usually,
baboons cry out when danger threatens,
but not in the glade.
Here,
they abandon their posts to follow danger.
In complete silence,
the kudu listen for a warning call.
Silence signals safe passage.
And so,
the kudu enter the kill zone.
Not a sound.
And all the while,
she steals closer.
Last chance to warn.
Betrayal is complete.
The glade pride will eat well today,
thanks to the baboons.
Why,
against all natural instincts,
do these baboons remain silent when lions prowl?
What's in it for the baboons?
If a hungry lion is a dangerous lion,
a lion with a full belly is a safer lion.
Keep the glade pride fed,
and there may be peace between natural enemies.
It could be as simple as that.
And so it is in this bend in the river,
called the Glade,
a very special place.
But trouble is on the way.
Massive herds of buffalo forced to leave
the parched highlands in search of water.
Are being drawn like magnets to the glade.
The buffalo collective is
a thirsty,
sprawling mass of brawn and horn.
They're being shadowed by
an unusual pride of lions.
The Unja,
Buffalo Soldier,
aggressive,
unpredictable,
worthy of respect.
The injar have their measure.
They are in tune with the nature of the herd.
Their territory is boundless
because it's constantly on the move.
The injar pride consider the
buffalo to be their territory.
The Anjar have perfected the
dark art of the buffalo kill.
They
seek the vulnerable.
Hidden at the heart of this herd
are the young and the injured.
The injar will weed them out.
An injured calf.
Target locked.
Push the soldiers forward.
Spirit the young one away
under cloak of shadow and dust.
They make it look easy.
An injured calf's misfortune.
One less to slow the buffalo down.
The herd grows stronger.
Would they march onward to the
glade in the heat of the day?
The injah never far behind.
The injah,
a lean and mean.
Power-hungry drifters.
They have taken the vulnerable from the herd.
Now they will take on the soldiers.
Oh.
The
injar live off the buffalo.
This herd belongs to them.
A
cheetah is watching the injars herd,
but she is not interested in the buffalo.
She's looking for hangers-on,
impala that shadow the herd,
masked behind a veil of false security.
A superb hunter and a mother,
she is a cheetah in lion country,
where cubs rarely survive.
So far,
she's raised three.
Risk of lion attack on her family is
great.
Hunger drives the cheetah on.
She has a long way to travel before she can hunt.
The impala will soon abandon the plains,
together with the buffalo,
all on the same journey.
Drawn to the last waters of the glade,
one thirsty buffalo herd,
six hundred strong,
shadowed by the inja.
Always on the move,
cubs in tow.
The injar will follow the
buffalo wherever they take them,
even into other lions'
territories.
They are the injar.
Guardians of the gates of the glade,
an ancient forest of baobab trees.
Some have survived hundreds of years,
standing witness to the
change of countless seasons.
Baobab forest provides for all.
There is great power here.
This forest is the territory of the
biggest lion pride in all of Ruaha.
The Baobab pride.
More than thirty members,
numbers far above the ordinary,
powerful lioness hunters and their offspring,
and the baobab forest provides
for every one of them.
The first buffalo herd of the dry
season arrives in the Baobab forest.
This is not the Injara pride's buffalo.
This herd has come from the north.
Over a thousand strong,
the babar pride relies on the
annual arrival of the buffalo.
But this time,
the herd is not stopping in the forest.
Thirst drives the parched buffalo
on to the waters of the glade.
If the beaupré pride follows,
they will leave their forest,
trespass into the glade pride's territory.
Forbidden territory.
Unable to resist the
temptation of hunting buffalo,
they leave the safety of their sanctuary.
Glade pride lionesses have witnessed the
arrival of the buffalo countless times.
It's been many months since the grunt and grind
of the great herds last shattered their peace.
But this time,
something is different.
The sound of too many hooves,
heading from opposite directions.
Two herds of buffalo are marching on the glade.
The one herd from the baobab forest,
from the west,
the injars herd.
It's not the masses of thirsty
beasts that concern the glade pride.
It's what follows.
It's their own kind they fear,
a threat to their cubs.
Just a small pride,
but wise mothers many times over.
The old lionesses know from experience
that behind all that dust and noise,
other lions follow.
With a lust to kill,
the family must leave its paradise for now.
They will be back,
but not before peace returns
under the false protection of the buffalo.
The impala are delivered
to the waters of the glade.
Desperation delivers the cheetahs.
The mother cheetah must make a kill.
Her hungry cubs depend on it.
To hunt in a lion pride's
territory is to invite attack.
Right now,
she has a narrow window of opportunity,
because the glade pride is not here,
but the baboons are.
And if they spot her,
they will raise the alarm.
She must wait for the impala to drink.
To move away from the baboons.
Hunger pushes a cub forward.
Threatens their cover.
The act,
unseen.
No more risks.
The cubs must stay.
Learn this lesson from afar.
A life lesson.
A quick kill,
to survive.
The baboons will decide who kills here.
The cheetah retreats.
She's not geared for combat.
The baboons will send poachers
back to where they came from.
A successful kill would have meant
life for a family of cheetahs.
Still,
she breathes in the shadow of a
creature with dubious motives,
ally of the glade lions.
Is this curiosity or concern?
Oh,
oh,
oh.
Even they are surprised when
she springs back to life.
The baboons expelled a poacher.
Their intervention has saved a life.
Strange things happen in the glade.
The herd from the Bayabab
forest floods into the riverbed.
The pathfinders lead them
into the heart of the glade.
Perfect storm,
as the injars herd descends
on the very same water,
and two mighty buffalo herds become one.
They come with a thirst that will only be
conquered when every last
buffalo has had its fill.
Confrontation with the enemy is inevitable,
but the outcome is not,
because now their force has doubled.
The babar pride arrives in the glade,
trespasses in the forbidden territory.
Temptation,
too great.
Their fate is sealed.
They will hunt in the glade,
search for weak spots.
Split up.
Wait for the right moment to attack.
The soldiers sense impending danger,
lurking somewhere in the sands.
Break cover.
Create a stampede.
Probe for weakness.
Split
the herd.
Drive them out of the riverbed.
A
mistake.
Trapped.
Buffalo,
take it to the lions.
Oh.
Bea-Bab lions have made two fundamental errors.
They chose to hunt in.
In the hottest part of the day,
and they attack the buffalo
before they'd finished drinking.
Belligerent buffalo can take the
heat and will fight to drink.
How long can the lions hold position?
One determined young lioness still
has the energy to test the herd.
This could be the first and
last buffalo she ever attacks.
In
the heart of forbidden territory,
hungry,
hot,
exhausted,
hopes of bounty evaporating fast.
The Beababs have given all they have to give,
but there is more to come.
The Anjar pride has arrived,
and they don't like what they see.
A large pride of strange lions
is holding their buffalo at bay.
The injar is not the biggest pride,
but these lions are ferocious.
A babab lioner spots the injar entering the glade.
There is nothing but pure
foreboding in their advance.
Now,
two prides in the forbidden territory.
Baab Bab lionesses on alert.
Nja in position.
A young Anjar male breaks the ranks.
Instinct drives him forward.
His first encounter with
female strangers in the flesh.
Baabab lionesses challenge his insolence.
An adult male would never
tolerate a lioness's defiance,
but there are no adult males here.
Lionesses dominate both prides.
And the injar leader is the most
powerful lioness of them all.
There can be no retreat.
Every member of both prides
will have to fight this battle.
Their futures are at stake.
The
buffalo sense it.
The glade,
giver of life,
is about to become an arena of war.
Oh.
The
injar have the edge.
Beaube Pride,
the largest pride in all of Ruaha,
driven out of the glade.
But there are worse things than being beaten.
One of their own has been left behind.
The young.
Young Linus,
who tried to prove her worth as a buffalo hunter,
has been taken hostage by the injah.
They
could kill her right now.
Instead,
they torture.
Her cries of suffering stop
the bayabab pride's retreat.
The defeated watch and listen.
As the torment continues.
There is only one way to stop the torture.
The bear bab pride must submit to the inja.
The lions must return to the battleground.
The bayabab pride leader could
be entering a trap.
Still,
she goes forward.
To stop the pain,
alone she stands to put an end
to the lioness's suffering.
The bear Babliya lays down in complete
submission before her Njarka counterpart.
Too late for bravado.
The injah have what they want.
They've taught the beabab pride a lesson.
Stay away from their buffalo.
The beababs have their lioness back.
Her injuries are severe.
Can she stand?
Defeated by battle,
and now by heat,
the pride moves off to the
edge of the glade to wait.
Give the injured lioness a chance.
The fearless leader risked her
life to submit to the injar.
All in vain.
The heat is sucking up the
last energy in the glade.
The leader has no choice.
Time for the pride to return to their territory,
the Beabab forest.
Torn between the pride and
the bond with her daughter,
the mother is the last to go.
She stayed as long as she can,
but
it's the heat that drives her away.
Oh,
oh,
Last breath taken in the glade.
Nothing can change what happened in these sands.
Buffalo now drink their fill in
the golden hours of the glade.
Fortunes
change.
Life is taken and given again.
The glade lionesses return with their cubs.
Her body,
all that's left to show what happened here.
Oh.
A young stranger.
There's
a lesson here.
Awaken,
more powerful strangers,
formidable hunters,
on their way to the glade.